<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Annotations upon the late protestation: or, A true character of an affectionate minde to King and Parliament.</title>
            <author>T. L.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88813</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L67</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E114_28</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22327</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871710</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871710</idno>
            <idno type="VID">124125</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88813)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 124125)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 20:E114[28])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Annotations upon the late protestation: or, A true character of an affectionate minde to King and Parliament.</title>
                  <author>T. L.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: T. L.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from Thomason Coll.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August. 27".</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:124125:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ANNOTATIONS UPON THE LATE PROTESTATION: OR, A TRUE CHARACTER of an affectionate minde to <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Feare God and honour the King.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere is a command from above by the Supreme power touching himſelf and his Lievtenant, which Lievtenant of the Lords being his Majeſtie, whoſe power comming from above, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Viceroy to the Supreme, he is to be obeyed in all juſt commands in obedience to the higheſt powers, For <hi>the powers that be, are ordained of God, and they that ſhall reſiſt the powers, reſiſteth th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ordinance of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:124125:2"/>
            <p> And S. <hi>Peter</hi> teacheth us in his firſt Epiſtle ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Chapter, ver. 13. That we ſhould <hi>Submit our ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to King as Supreme, or unto Governours</hi> as the two Honourable Houſes of Parliament, which are called by the King and ſet up by him for the puniſhment of evill doers, and for the reward of them that doe well: For ſo is the will of God that with well-doing you may put to ſilence the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of fooliſh men.</p>
            <p>Now for he whomſoever he be that ſhall ſet himſelfe againſt the Parliament a pleader and great paines taker for the King and Common-wealth, who by them were choſen and with their approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſtand to their judgement what they ſhall in their wiſdomes doe in our behalfe, I ſay, he that ſhall ſet himſelfe in the leaſt manner to wrong a member of that Honourable Houſe of Lords or Commons in their lawfull employments by either of the Houſes for the honour of God, and his Religion, ſafetie of his Majeſties perſon, and the good of his country is an abſolute traytour.</p>
            <p>For he that will firſt chooſe his advocate and then betray him, toucheth the apple of Gods owne eye, and it were better for him that a milſtone were hanged about his neck, and he caſt into the depth of the ſea.</p>
            <p>How mad then are thoſe Cavaliers who are without grace or the feare of the Almightie, which no doubt but are borne in ſome ſhires or counties of this Kingdome, and have both Knights of their ſhires and Burgeſſes of their Corporations to ſtand for their good and welfare as well as for the good of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:124125:2"/> the very wives of their owne boſome, and children of their owne bodies, we muſt not then kill theſe men, ſeeing we have choſen them for our ſubſtitutes in Parliament, we muſt not hurt them, God forbid we ſhould; and they that ſhall go about or attempt, or adviſe upon ſuch ungodly actions, tending to the wrong of his bleſſed Majeſtie or the Parliament, now ſhall they thinke or looke to eſcape the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of Eternall fire, for S. <hi>John</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle, Chap. 3. ver. 15. ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever hateth his brother is a murtherer, and ye know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that no murtherer hath eternall life abiding in him;</hi> and in the ſecond Chapter of the ſame Epiſtle he ſaith, <hi>If any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him,</hi> and if the love of the Father is not in that man that loveth the world, then ſurely the Father hateth and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that man that will ſet upon his neighbour, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or countryman, and kill him out of a meere love to the things of this world, and for the things of this world, abſolutely the men of theſe courſes love not God nor his Religion, if they ſay they doe, they are lyars; S. <hi>John</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle, Chap. 4. ver. 20. ſo ſaith, <hi>For he that loveth not his brother whom he hath ſeen, how can he love God, whom he hath not ſeen?</hi> Now to run againſt the 6. Commandement of God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie wilfully is no ſmall ſin, and to kick againſt ſo ſtrong a thorne iſſuing from ſo great a hand.</p>
            <p>And whoſoever he be, that ſhall not grant his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie his right, and that which doth truly belong unto Caeſar is an abſolute enemie to the King and Common-wealth, and a ſower of ſedition, for our Saviour Chriſt himſelfe ſaith, <hi>Give unto Caſar that which is Caeſars, and to God that which is Gods,</hi> that is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:124125:3"/> that which belongeth to the Lord in his due Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and that to him muſt be given; and that which is the due of the people, they ought to have by the very ſame rule of our Saviour Chriſt: for he that would have Caeſar have his due, wils alſo that God in his members ſhould have their right alſo, the one as well as the other, the Lord is ſo mercifull that he would have both have their due rights without go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together by the eares, and they that doe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are Phariſaicall like, making a queſtion what belongs unto Caeſar, and what not, as if people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing maſters in Iſrael and knew not theſe things, which if they did not, then they were not liable to the cenſure of our Saviour Chriſt, who telleth all and every one that knoweth the will of his maſter and doth it not, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes; and what ſimple Gentleman is there in combuſtion and in traitoriſme, ſetting his Majeſtie againſt the Ordinance of Parliament, but is ſenſible of a Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by law and guiltie of high treaſon againſt the State, and that moſt palpably; for he that will chuſe his friend in truſt for him in Parliament, in hope of his fidelitie to him, as well as for his owne ſelfe, wife and children, and if any of theſe men or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhall riſe up againſt any of his or their Parliament men <hi>advocates,</hi> or any of his neighbouring counties advocates and Parliament men, and not be content to ſtand to the judgement of their beſt endevours, and to helpe them againſt all their oppoſites and againſt unequall and unworthy perſons, they are much to be blamed, and traitours to the State, who will not juſtifie and aſſiſt the Houſes of Parliament in their Councels and judgements againſt all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:124125:3"/> contrary to the Law of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> for his part he wiſhes them to be marked that are the cauſe of the diviſion both in the Church and Common-wealth, and they that trouble the true Proteſtant Religion, the way to everlaſting life; the very ſame Apoſtle wiſheth, they were even cut off.</p>
            <p>And to trample upon the Crown, which God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid any one ſhould, it is to touch the Lords anointed, and there is an expreſſe command againſt this from the Lord, who ſaith, <hi>Touch not mine anointed and doe my Prophets no harme:</hi> and no honeſt man will doe this, that is, to wrong his Majeſty, for if his Majeſtie hath not his immunities, how ſhall we be ſettled in our proprieties.</p>
            <p>It is againſt reaſon and civill honeſty for Judges to take all the right that is due to them to be ſure, and not to allow their Neighbours their juſt rights and priviledges. Or is it equitie for a Taylour to looke on one ſide of him, where his hell is under his ſhopboard to throw his piece of ſilver-cloth, he hath over and above his Maſters worke, and not looke on the other ſide of him to thinke it is his Cuſtomers, he muſt not take it, which to doe is blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe without ſeeing honeſty.</p>
            <p>Now for as much as his Majeſty and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath tyed themſelves each to other in an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham-like</hi> Covenant, not to paſſe the limits of their own bounds, in which they have ſet and tyed voluntarily their own ſelves, and hath erected to all the world in print a Proteſtation to that purpoſe and both parties interchangeably by ſolemn vowes and promiſes in the preſence of Almighty God hath
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:124125:4"/> vowed to ſtand faſt and to ſtick in honour each to other, till life ſhall depart; and that they will hold the one to the other for better for worſe, for richer for poorer, goods and all laid down in the Covenant of their promiſe one for the other, for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the true Proteſtant Religion, and both their Honours, ſafetie, and Priviledges each of other: And if theſe two new betrothed turtle Doves by ſo ſolemn a vow made between themſelves, ſhall peck one at another, as they begin too much to doe, (God of his mercy help them) and be impatient one with another, and not keep their bills out of anothers eyes, they will too much wrong themſelves, like man and wife who quickly and too often forget themſelves in their matrimoniall Contract, and by their long jangling at laſt part, and lay the key under doores and run away. So if the King and Parliament ſhall forget their ſo ſerious Proteſtation, vow and profeſſion one truly taken for and in the behalf of the other, in declaration of the tenderneſſe of honour and true affection each to other, and now not bearing one with another in love, nor ſubmit in this pleaſant knot of agreement in mind each with the other like <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> this were deplorable, (ſaith the Divine) and wonderfull. Here the Vncle for quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſake ſubmits his honour in his hoary hairy head to his greene headed Nephew with a motion that there may be no falling out becauſe (ſaid he) we are Brethren.</p>
            <p>So his Majeſtie and his Honourable Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament what an eaſie matter were it for theſe two Turtle Doves, ſympathizing in affection, ſay but ſo much as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> did one to the other, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:124125:4"/> why, becauſe by faith ſurely Brethren in Chriſt; all then would be ended if but this ſpirit of humilitie were in them both. There was a very low ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſpirit betweene the <hi>Scots</hi> and us, and ſhall not there be the like between his Majeſty and his neereſt people; will his Majeſty be worſe to his owne and beſt loving people than the <hi>Scots.</hi> And if we ſhall fall out upon earth will not the Father in Heaven be angry, who hath ſent his Goſpel of peace amongſt us teaching of us that if poſſible, we ſhould have <hi>peace with all men,</hi> will it not then diſpleaſe the Lord that we have learned no more Religion, nor be no more endued with faith and patience, but goe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſhed the bloud one of another, to the ſhame of our Nation, and hiſſing to other Kingdomes, let it not <hi>be told in Gath, nor publiſhed in Aſhkelon.</hi> Theſe beginnings of warre on neither ſide are fruits of the Spirit, it may be thought, for <hi>the fruits of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit are love, patience, meekneſſe, forgiving one another, forbearing one with another.</hi> And let it be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred what <hi>Abner</hi> ſaid to <hi>Joab, ſhall the ſword devoure for ever, how long will it be ere thou call back the people from following of their Brethren, knoweſt thou not that it will be bitterneſſe in the end?</hi> ſo it is wiſhed by the people of the Lord, that <hi>bloud touch not bloud.</hi> And Sir <hi>Benjamen Ruddyards</hi> ſpeech is excellent to this purpoſe and worthy of note, the Parliament un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly will not doe amiſſe to hearken to thoſe grave lines and worthy ſpeech of his.</p>
            <p>H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s firſt Speech was for Religion, and the ſetling of the Church of God, in the very firſt place of all but it is not I thinke a man may be bold to ſay, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:124125:5"/>
            <p> Now his ſecond Speech is againſt ſhedding of bloud, the defiling of the Land. To have a whole Land deſiled with blood, a moſt wonderfull and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable thing; and Chriſtians bloud is of a deepe dye, were it amiſſe then if green heads would take gravitie along with them in all their actions, who moſt reſemble the Image of their maker, and hoary hairs is a crown of glory being found in the way of righteouſneſſe; and to heare a grave old religious and wiſe Gentleman ſpeak and giving advice and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, it is as it were, if ſeriouſly conſidered, God Almighty himſelf in a Crown of glory giving good counſell to the younger. Was it not the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſpake with the people of Iſrael in the mouth of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and was it not the Lord in <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſpake un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Brethren concerning his bones, and was it not the Lord in <hi>Solomon</hi> which ſpake unto the people concerning the building of a houſe to his name; and certainly it is the Lord that ſpeaks from the mouth of wiſe and grave righteous men to the yonger ſort to learne wiſedome.</p>
            <p>And if a Crowne of glory ſhall not be heard ſpeak who can one better hear; Green heads deſire to be heard, ſome for their owne ends, and ſome for their owne applauſe in the world, but an auncient grave man ſpeaking, queſtionleſſe looks not either for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, or affection in the right hand or on the left but ſtrait forward becauſe he is going forward to God Almighty to receive his pay for the pains of his labour whoſe works ſhall follow him.</p>
            <p>And ſo much for the hearing of gravitie: Now for that we have taken a Proteſtation, every one ought ſeriouſly to conſider the burden of a vow is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:124125:5"/> upon us, and that vow too, in which is included that we ſhould endeavour and ſtudy the peace of the three Kingdomes, and yet notwithſtanding now ſo ſolemne Proteſtation in the ſight of God and man, touching amitie and peace in this our Kingdome, yet there is a thouſand times more rumours of wars now then before our Proteſtation. What were we like <hi>Peter,</hi> ſtrong in the faith when we made this Proteſtation, and now when we ſhould ſtick cloſe to it, be weak like <hi>Peter</hi> not remembring we have made a Covenant with the Lord, not onely to hate Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and to decline from it as much as in us lyeth, but alſo includes the undertakers thereof every one that he ſhould ſtudy and labour for peace ſo much as in every one of us lyeth, and ſeriouſly conſider of our Proteſtation, and be ever and alwayes, now and then looking upon it, and look up unto our Saviour Chriſt as he lookt back upon <hi>Peter,</hi> and pray to him that we may keep our reſolution.</p>
            <p>And it is very good for the Cavaliers about the King ſeriouſly to conſider of it and ſo to doe, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe any that ſhall attempt his Majeſty to take up armes againſt his <hi>Parliament,</hi> and aske them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves if they have not taken the Proteſtation, if not, it were good they did, and not divide themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the body of the Kingdome by flattering of his Majeſty to goe againſt his <hi>Parliament;</hi> and they that have taken it, let them conſider a vow is upon them.</p>
            <p>Apparantly the Marqueſſe of <hi>Harford</hi> and Lord <hi>Paulet</hi> hath broken down the ridges of their ſo ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Proteſtation, in breaking of his Majeſties peace in falling upon the Yeomanrie in <hi>Somerſet-ſhire.</hi> Now what more diſpleaſing to God Almighty than
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:124125:6"/> breach of Covenants and of peace one to the other, when they ſhall take the Lord to be a witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them of their untruths one to the other; then what a caſe are thoſe Gentlemen in, (let them call themſelves to remembrance, that are with the King and the Marqueſſe o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Harford</hi> and the Lord <hi>Paulet,</hi> who have broken the Covenant of peace before God and the people; and them that doe intend the leaſt thought of diſhonour to the Kings <hi>Parliament,</hi> have they not ſeriouſly taken the Proteſtation, in which is included the peace of the Kingdome, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Religion, King and Parliament, and the vow and proteſtation taken for the honour of the one, is the ſame vow and proteſtation for the honour of the other; and they that ſhall vow, and yet in ſhew hold for the honour of the head, and not the body, diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours the head by flatterie, by endeavouring to ſet it off from the body by ſeditious and evil counſell, and they that goe about any ſuch thing, doe greatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour their Countrey and Kingdome, whoſe own houſes by ſinne is laid waſt, ſo they would have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo; For the Head hath called the body poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique of the Kingdome together, deſiring the ſame to be joyn<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to its head for its help, comfort and lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it up in his ſtraits, who was ready to fall, and weary with holding up, looking upon the <hi>Scots,</hi> like <hi>Moſes</hi> hands againſt the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> that <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> was faine to take the pains for him to hold them up; and now the <hi>Aarons</hi> and the <hi>Hurs</hi> of our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome being called upon the Mount, I mean to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> to conſolate and lift up the head of our Soveraigne, and ſo long as our <hi>Aarons</hi> and <hi>Hurs</hi> are upon the Mount, and our Head and Soveraign lyeth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:124125:6"/> his head upon their ſhoulders they by the bleſſing of God will bear him out of the bitter waters of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> and ſweet ſhall be his reſt. I will flatly forbid the bloud-thirſty Cavaliers ſay ſo much, upon whom if his Majeſty repoſe, is to be feared it will be but a pillow of briars and thorns beſpattred with bloud. Now if there be any that ſhall be ſo ungodly that hath taken this Proteſtation for the honour of King and <hi>Parliament,</hi> and yet ſhall performe but halfe his vow, and half his worſhip and honour, but to one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of both, who have indeed inſeparably united themſelves by their ſolemn vow and Proteſtation which no way they can reverſe, and ſeek to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his Majeſties favour and affection from his <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> and <hi>Hurs,</hi> and from repoſing upon his own Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, perſwading of his Majeſty to hearken to the dammee blades of the time, the way of undoing his Kingdome, they may goe and take <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira</hi> by the hand, and it is thought ſome have taſted of the ſame ſuddain death they did; And my Lord Marqueſſe, it is conceived, hath very hardly leapt this pit-fall, and if <hi>Paulet</hi> ſcape and many more, they have great cauſe to magnifie the mercy and patience of God towards ſuch wretches.</p>
            <p>And for Kings, <hi>Solomon</hi> he ſaith, It is an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for them not to hold and keepe Covenant, vowes and Proteſtations. And hath not <hi>Spaine</hi> made her ſelfe more hatefull to the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> and other Nations, nay to the very Heathen by the breach of her truce and Covenants, then ever other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhe would have done, this verifies the truth of the word of the Lord, which ſaith, <hi>It is odious for Kings to lye.</hi> And in the 5. of <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>It is</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:124125:7"/> 
               <hi>better for a man not to vow, than to vow and not to pay,</hi> for God taketh not pleaſure in ſuch kinde of weake Proteſtations, nor people who are raſhly taken up with the mouth, and no more think upon them with hearts, but bids us <hi>pay that which we have vowed;</hi> And I pray God we may all ſo doe, and that the Lord may delight in us to doe us good.</p>
            <p>And this by the way, he is the true hearted man that is for the King and Parliament, and all other are meerly inſinuating and wicked flatterers, aiming at a little deceitfull favour to accompliſh their owne ends, which at the beſt is bad enough, as my Lord of <hi>Straffords</hi> was, who with all his deep councell holding ſo much againſt the Common-wealth, and endevoring to bring in an Arbitrary government, contrary to the liberty of the Subject, went to the grave without his head, a wiſe man would think it a very faire example to keep out of Princes books, and be not ſo vile as to adviſe Kings againſt their Subjects, from whom they have under God their daily bread both King and ill flatterers too, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Common-wealth ought to be loved not hunted nor laid in ambuſh for: And if the Kings bleſſed Majeſtie and his honourable Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament did but ſeriouſly conſider of their new Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimoniall knot and Covenant in which they have ſo ſolemnly tyed themſelves by their owne free vowes and joynt conſents each to other, and what faithfull Proteſts and Promiſes they have made one to the other and for the other, which I beſeech God of heaven they may doe, and lay the Proteſtation both of them to their hearts, and but weigh their actions one as well as the other, and their words to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:124125:7"/> it will ſurely cauſe no more falling out, but a neerer uniting of Prince and people together in love, when they ſhall looke and freſh call to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance what new Covenants the Head and the members have made for the honour and ſafetie one of another, all which may be eaſily done in laying of the Proteſtation in print before them, then fall out they cannot, nay with leave they dare not.</p>
            <p>A Proteſtation is taken, and vowes are made on both ſides, but are they not caſt behinde the backe, and out of ſight out of minde. I remember the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſaid when the people were a taking the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, that they ſhould each of them buy one of them, and ſticke them up in ſome places of their houſes, which I conceive from him was after the manner as God commanded the Iſraelites to doe with his Lawes, to the end that they might be ever now and then a looking upon them; that ſo they might better remember and think upon them in the field, and in the houſe, what a ſolemne vow, promiſe and Proteſtation they have taken in the preſence of Almightie God that thereby they might be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter put in minde to keepe them: and when this ſhall be ſeriouſly pondered and conſidered of, with <hi>Cain,</hi> though he longs to have his fingers knockle deep in his brothers blood, as ſome have had too too much alreadie, could be able to ſeparate <hi>Ruth</hi> from <hi>Boaz, Shem</hi> from <hi>Japhet,</hi> the King from his faithfull Ones the Parliament; the Royall Head from ſo amiable a bodie, <hi>ecce ſignum,</hi> their paines and money with the hazard of their deareſt blood, and ſequeſtring of themſelves from their deare wives and ſweet Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to attaine and win, and bring home their belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:124125:8"/> King who is led away by the wild boares of the Forreſt, to the mountaines of Lebanon, Shinar and Hermon, where they keep him in the Lions den and among the mountaines of the Leopards.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the bodie Politick hath wooed along time the Head to come in and to be joyned to the ſame, that it may not be miſcarryed, nor loſe out of it that rich gliſtering Diamond which yet praiſed be God ſtickes faſt to it, even Ireland.</p>
            <p>I remember very well what a Scottiſh Miniſter ſaid in <hi>Delph</hi> long ſince, and I cannot hold it in, That when a King or people refuſe to heare Councell and advice, and refuſe the harkning one to the other to be adviſed one by the other, it was he ſaid a ſigne God had appointed ſome deſtruction there, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech God it be not ſo now here among us, for the King will neither heare nor be adviſed by his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, nor his Councell will not heare nor hearken to the ſeverall Declarations of the King, but be at ſo great diſtance one from off the other, as if they were afraid one of another, and no body praiſed be God is about to hurt them, if they would be but quiet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween themſelves, and it is deplorable to think how that the King and Parliament hath vowed and ſworn each to other in love, and yet ſhould ſo quickly in one twelve moneths forget, as they ſeem to do, their ſolemne tye one to another, and in ſtead of being true and faithfull friends each to other, begin to wrangle between themſelves neere daggers drawing and about that too which ſhould be for both their ſafeties againſt our enemies, even the <hi>Militia,</hi> God of heaven helpe us, is the cauſe of our combuſtion, and God forbid that that which the Lord hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:124125:8"/> us for our preſervation ſhould be for our deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Now the way to prevent the miſchiefe is that all the Counties of <hi>England</hi> joyne as one man, not croſſing nor wrangling one with another, but as you did all Petition for the <hi>Militia</hi> to the Parliament for the ſetting of your Counties in a poſture of ſafety for the defence of his Majeſtie in theſe troubleſome times, and the Kingdome, ſo you would beſeech his Majeſties favour not to be againſt nor goe about to croſſe his Parliaments proceeding, who ſtudies night and day for his good; and call in his Commiſſion of Array which makes the diſturbance, and his mad Cavaliers which breake his Majeſties peace, and will begger his Majeſtie, if he be not carefull of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; as his Majeſtie, I hope, will begger the Papiſts who lend him money to undoe himſelfe, and if they could would have him fight againſt the Proteſtants, his loving Subjects, which into my heart it cannot enter, that ſo pious and ſo gracious a King will do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracious actions too, nay he cannot doe it belonging to God, for the Child of God cannot ſin, and <hi>Paul</hi> in the <hi>Romanes</hi> ſaith, he ſhall not, for he there ſaith, <hi>Sin ſhall not have dominion over him,</hi> where now is then the ſimple Papiſts vaine hopes.</p>
            <p>Theſe things moſt humbly are ſtudied not that the chiefe Cedar of this our Lebanon our gracious King, and the other attendant lower Cedar knowes not what is made in Promiſes, Vowes and Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions each to the other, and is paſt betweene them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but this is humbly, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> in another caſe ſpeakes, to put high and low, rich and poore in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:124125:9"/> remembrance knowing we muſt ſhortly all leave this tabernacle as the Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore in the feare of the Lord caſt away ſtrife, anger, envie, debate, hatred, bickering, with jeering one at another, and beare one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers burden in love, and ſo fulfill the Law of Chriſt, and be joyfull Head and members all one in another, and rejoyce together, and I ſay rejoyce.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The truly well affected to the honour and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe both of his ſacred Majeſtie the King, and both Honourable Houſes of Parliament, humbly ſo prayeth</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
